Let me just zip up and then away we go.
Good afternoon.
My name is Patrick Lichty.
I'm with Winona State
Creative Digital Media with
and David Heckman.
And I'm going to be talking about
some more of my ideas
on spatial writing and digital
button beliefs.
I'm writing inside the box,
looking at the idea
of creative exigencies
and local virtual space.
The museum in the pocket.
Between 1935 and 1941, Duchamp
compressed his entire over
into a portable leather valise.
Museum and luggage opened on any table
wherever he was going to go.
Took him seven years to make it.
Wasn't necessarily an archival gesture,
but a proposition about the artwork
as context institution
in the body of the artist who carries
both of them
had about 69 pieces of work in it.
It took the studio and institution
creation exhibition into a single object.
He made about 300 copies of these,
which he distributed.
And these were each
each one of these in Museum Object.
Here's the Boynton voice,
one copy of it.
So let's go over to the
buys like quest three or the
I or things like that.
So think about the valise.
You know, in other words, it's finished.
It's, you know, a museum exhibition.
It's codified.
Has music ministers have completed works
open on any table?
The visor is potentially
a perpetually generative pounced,
but can be updated at any time.
The space in which the word work is made,
stored, annotated and exhibited.
And it's basically strapped your head
open to your eyes, the body.
So the shared condition is compression
of institutional space
into personal portable form.
Now this takes four movements
in this argument that I have.
We already talked about Duchamp.
The Boyden believes
as a theoretical precedent,
the portable institution,
the portable studio
for Hagglund,
who we're going to talk about in a minute.
Writing in through the theory
of multi-dimensional text,
similar to things like Holtzman.
Engelbart, and.
Nelson.
We'll go to Dini, Gregor,
and talking about archival
practice as a model for simultaneous
creation and preservation.
And Daniel Brown in regards to modular
object oriented interfaces,
as a grammar for spatial thinking.
So I'm thinking about here is
that is not a new
delivery platform itself to create
literary for existing literary forms,
but a new institutional formation,
what I call the local virtual.
So let's go from Marcel
Duchamp to Schwitters compression
versus expansion.
So with the Boynton valise, we've got
the museum folded into a box,
a counter institution placing
curatorial authority with the artist,
not the museum.
And let's think about Schwitters
is museum.
I mean, apartment installation.
The bell is the studio grown
into a total spatial bounces
across three iterations
across three countries of exile.
So if we think
about the metaphor,
it shares this character. It's
always unfinished, always accumulating,
always available for reorganization.
So the headset as kind of
local virtual Merz Bell.
This brings us to that subject
the local virtual.
So in other words,
we're not dealing with networked
cloud based models working.
We're living on corporate servers
like Wix etc.
you know, access through intermediaries.
The local virtual insists on the visor
as a self-sufficient environment,
the author's entire creative apparatus
and present in the space immediately
surrounding the body.
This isn't necessarily
a technical preference,
but an ontological statement
about the creative environment,
embodied practice,
and processes settings.
So spatial writing for the haggling.
So the standard metaphor for writing
is the line.
Even hypertext kept itself
is something that, you know
in a way, you read through a path,
through a set of two dimensional graphs.
Hagan's
liquid text and experiments
proposed text as multidimensional, meaning
emerging from spatial relationships
proximity, layering, superimposition.
That, of course, comes from Douglas
Engelbart, then through Ted Nelson
with his.
Do and also through
Steven Holtzman and his perspective
you browser system.
So precedents not only these things
that I'm talking about.
You know, like like Nelson and Holtzman
and that's sort of thing.
But Benjamin, the Arcades Project
as a kind of a literary montage,
you know, that you can go from one
to the other, etc.
then also Dick Hagan's intermedia graph,
then Stephanie Strickland's active reader,
you know,
now and others we're talking about,
you know, the,
you know, the practitioner
who is an active author.
So to me, these spatial decisions are
literary decisions or creator decisions.
You know, the practice
more towards choreography or sculpture
than the conventional writing.
And this goes from also Aaron
Manning's thought,
you know, in,
you know, in motion cognition.
So the archive is practice the problem.
Michael Joyce is after me a story.
I lived inside story space,
you know, a floppy disk, a max, a mac,
you know, preserving.
And the work is to preserve the apparatus.
As the apparatus vanishes,
the work becomes unreadable.
You know, an interpretive context is gone.
This is kind of the same
with William Gibson's Agrippa.
You know, a story.
In other words, as you read it,
it gets a erase off the floppy disk.
Danny Gregor with,
you know, the next lab, Pathfinders.
You're rebooting literature, Ayelet,
you know, preservation
as active maintenance, closer
to curatorial performance
than literary silence
as science, a library science, sorry.
Rebuilding, reading communities
and interpretive frameworks.
So thing is,
is that in this idea of the local virtual,
the boundary between Archive and Attlee
dissolves.
You know,
also the archive making archiving
is a continuous co-present practice.
This brings me to Daniel Brown,
someone who I've been a big fan of
with like 25 years.
His idea of Noodle Box,
which was in an interface in flash.
So in many ways you would build interfaces
in Noodle Box through these different
chunks of, you know, informational
typologies like media, text, etc.
and you'd be thinking through the hands.
You know, noodle box, you'd be using
this module interface to kind of create
informational cities by manipulating
kind of chunks of thought itself.
This kind of goes into the idea of Manning
and Aaron Manning's idea of body,
you know, movement as thought, not
the execution of thoughts already formed.
So and this goes through the idea of,
of informational objects that commands.
So the author is an issuing commands
so that a document, they pick it up,
move it, place it in relation and perceive
the meaning of a new configuration.
Terence McKenna
also talked about this in terms of,
you know, a VR fantasy
in which grammar was turned
into geometric shapes and it would,
you know, kind of form around you
as you would you would talk
so you could see what I mean.
But that's a different matter.
So additive revision
shuns reflective practitioner
new arrangements created alongside
old ones, a spatial version history
that reveals thinking as a sequence
of decisions, not a final product.
You have a trail.
So let's add
go to the end here a little bit
is that this is Robert Fill you, a French
Fluxus artist who spent a lot of time
in Vancouver and his museum
in the, in the, in the, in the bowler hat.
So this is you know, and then I also did
a video art in an iPod.
I did a voice in an iPod.
You know, this idea of Counter museum
counter network
has been repeating since the avant garde.
So the platform model,
you know, we look at the idea of work
on corporate servers,
archives, subject to terms of service
that change without notice,
an arrangement of serving
platforms, operate as serving
platform operators
and with creative dependance.
You know, kind of like Wix, by the way,
this is why I'm starting to create my own
static HTML websites
that can go anywhere.
So the local virtual
it's a portable institution belonging
to the author, archive drafts,
everything is in there.
And without the necessity for network
connection or platform mediation.
So in this case, I feel that Duchamp's
Valise was not an anti museum,
but a counter museum.
The local virtual is not an anti network,
it's a counter network
counter methods for creation and delivery.
So Duchamp opened his valise
on many tables.
And I think that we need to be able
to open the box
into our minds and around our bodies
in through the local virtual.
Thank you so much.
I'm Patrick and I'm from Winona State
University, creative Digital Media,
and I thank you for your time.